<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>researchupdate on Joshua Pughe-Sanford</title>
    <link>https://jpughesanford.github.io/tags/researchupdate/</link>
    <description>Recent content in researchupdate on Joshua Pughe-Sanford</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 12:00:32 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jpughesanford.github.io/tags/researchupdate/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Research Update October 4</title>
      <link>https://jpughesanford.github.io/posts/2019/10/research-update-october-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 12:00:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpughesanford.github.io/posts/2019/10/research-update-october-4/</guid>
      <description>This week was spent mostly working and fine tuning fellowship applications. That said, this week also required some careful thought into the phase space structure underlying extreme events. Previously, I had been converging a relative periodic orbit that seemed to lie in both the high dissipation and low dissipation regimes of the kolmogorov flow at $Re=40$. Both adjoint looping and direct newton iterations were used to try and converge this orbit, but both converged relatively slowly when compared to other RPOs converged at this Reynolds number and were stopped.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Update September 20</title>
      <link>https://jpughesanford.github.io/posts/2019/09/research-update-september-20/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2019 13:17:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpughesanford.github.io/posts/2019/09/research-update-september-20/</guid>
      <description>Using the quotient method as referenced in my previous update was unsuccesful. The dynamically relevant modes are rather different between the high-dissipation and low-dissipation lobes of the attractor. Modes that are common to both lobes tend to have pass through zero throughout the transitions between lobes, causing sparatic behavior in the quotienting method. There are well developed methods to bypass this issue in the literature, such as forming an atlas of charts on the full space, each chart describing a specific way to reduce the symmetry of its own section of the full space.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Update September 13</title>
      <link>https://jpughesanford.github.io/posts/2019/09/research-update-september-13/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2019 21:16:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpughesanford.github.io/posts/2019/09/research-update-september-13/</guid>
      <description>The majority of this weeks work was understanding the mechanism behind extreme events in the 2D Kolmogorov flow. These extreme are charactierized by short lived bursts ($\sim .3\ Jkg^{-1}s^{-1}$) in dissipation far above its expected value ($\sim .1\ Jkg^{-1}s^{-1}$).
The laminar state is possibly one of the most highly dissipitive states on the attractor, scaling as $\frac{1}{32}Re$ in my particular setup. Above $Re\sim10-20$, this state becomes unstable to states with lower dissipation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
